Hatem Ahmed Mohamed Abd El Salam

Jumeirah Lake Towers- Dubai Cell 00971543070465- 00201025829664 E-mail:Tommmy656@gmail.com titooo84@hotmail.com



<u>Personal</u> ID

Nationality : Egyptian citizen

Marital Status : Married Gender : Male

Date of Birth : 13/04/1984 Military Status : Exempted

Summary

I am a high energy, experienced hands on professional with strong management skills

I am self-motivated and I know what it takes to do a good job. I am excellent communicator and relationship builder, able to effectively interface with colleagues and the public. I provide sound understanding and hands on experience in product development and market analysis.

Experience

<u>Hilti Emirates L.L.C.</u> (From 01/06/2019 until present)

Hilti Emirates is a multinational co. for construction tools.

Credit, collection and billing Team leader

- 1 Preparing Monthly internal Audit for the AR team.
- 2 Preparing consolidated reports for discussions with sales teams on monthly basis.
- 3 Notifying the sales teams and AR about the slow payers and way to handle through a systematic pre-notified process.
- 4 Follow up on all the on old approved orders & rejecting the ones that are not needed.
- 5 Finishing all the procedures for raising legal cases and sending cases to external collectors.
- 6 Alignment and follow up meeting and calls with lawyers and external debt collection companies
- 7 Revise the customer accounts and align with sales manager on the way of dealing on future orders
- 8 Leading regional team as a project to provide a consolidated dashboard for both sales and finance weekly meetings, in addition to producing a booklet for new employees as training booklet that clarifies all the payment cycle in the company, approval cycles and SAP steps to ensure high efficient

- performance from new employees which is also useful for employees with less experience.
- 9 Managing project of introducing new legal offices and courier companies with better service and less cost.
- 10 Provide Training to new employees in finance & providing quarterly training sessions for finance background to employees outside finance.
- 11 Leading a team of 8 team members to ensure collection on time, provision reversal, payment allocation on time and sending complete customer invoices on time.
- 12 Reviewing received payments and ensures allocation on time based on customer's breakdown.
- 13 Changing 50% of the company focus customers from physical invoices to Electronic invoicing for better quality, less reconciliation issues and shorter collection cycle in addition to less cost.
- 14 Reviewing and approving Credit application forms and write off forms.
- 15 Analysis on customer new clustering, AR customer allocation, clustering customers based on sales of the rolling 12 months and required credit limit changes on Bi-annual basis.

<u>Kuehne + Nagel Regional office- Dubai</u> (FROM 01/05/2016 until 30/05/2019)

K+N is the biggest multinational freight forwarder for sea freight, air freight & overland services.

Regional Accounts receivable & credit risk Manager I am responsible about AR & Credit risk in 20 countries in middle east and Africa.

- 1-Reviewing AR balances for the big customers.
- 2-Provide workflow and SOP for process engineering once required.
- 3-Follow up our customer's issues, putting action plan and following up solution steps till solved.
- 4-Interfering on the escalation cases to agree with customers on payment plans.
- 5-Monitoring all AR KPIs, Overdue %, outstanding balance, excess of credit limit & bad Debts.
- 6-Revieweing the cash flow cycle for Middle East and Africa countries for the sake of better liquidity to be able to handle new targeted customer business.
- 7-Supervise all receivable accountants & solve their problems with their customers.
- 8-Selecting the high Risk customers for escalation cases.
- 9-Solving the high risk customer cases by deciding either to have legal case or insurance claim.
- 10-Responsible for Releasing & holding all the company shipments.
- 11-Analysing all credit requests after reviewing company financials, market reputation and ways to reduce the business risk.
- 12- Monitoring the high overdue customers discussing ways to improve either by holding shipments or by escalating to headquarters.

<u>Kuehne + Nagel freight forwarder</u> (FROM 1/12/2010 until 30/04/2016)

It's a multinational freight forwarder for sea freight, air freight & overland services.

Working Capital Manager

- 1-Preparing customer balance.
- 2-Revising the balance of all customers.
- 3-Follow up our customers & coordinate with operation department to solve customer problems.
- 4-Communicate with the customers to notify them with their balances & due dates
- 5-Sending a periodical aging report to sales managers & general manager to show our outcome & our performance during the past 2 weeks.
- 6-Follow all the company bank accounts
- 7-Supervise all receivable accountants & solve their problems with customers
- 8-Revise the bank with the system to make sure that they identical & have same transactions at same time.
- 9-Allocating all payments From Customers with their invoices.
- 10-Realasing & holding all the company shipments.
- 11-Reconciling all accounts with customers through reconciliation meetings

Alstom Egypt for Power and Transport Projects (From 01/05/2009 until 30/11/2010)

Alstom is a multinational co. for power plants & transport projects.

Senior Accountant

- 16 Preparing customer balance.
- 17 Preparing suppliers balance.
- 18 Notifying the cash accountant with the suppliers we have to pay them.
- 19 Follow up on all the shipments in the airport.
- 20 Finishing all the financial procedures on the company shipments.
- 21 Revising the cash expenses of all company sites.
- 22 Preparing monthly closing.
- 23 Controlling the open item list.
- 24 Filling all outstanding invoices
- 25 Filling all payments related to customers.
- 26 Responsible for payments to be done at the exact time.
- 27 Controlling the situation of all company projects.
- 28 Controlling shipments to know which had been received, which is not & when it should be received & re-export of shipment back to Germany & collecting security deposits from customs.

Gulf Agency Company (EGYPT) Ltd from (15/07/2006 until 30/04/2009) CSAV Norasia Group / Wan Hai Lines

It's a multinational shipping line & agency also

Accountant

- 1 Preparing customer balance
- 2 Preparing suppliers balance.
- 3 Recording the customer and suppliers entries in the ledger
- 4 Notifying the cash accountant with the suppliers we have to pay them
- 5 Recording the transactions balances in the supplier's ledgers.
- 6 Preparing revenues balance
- 7 Recording the revenues entries in the ledger
- 8 Balancing the transaction of the account of each journal
- 9 Recording the balance transactions in the ledger
- 10 Recording checks deposits
- 11 Preparing the balance of under collection checks.

Raya Contact Center (01/01/2006 until 01/05/2006)

It's a multinational Telecom company

International Account Rep:

- 1 Conducting Phone calls to attract new clients and cross-sell our good services To existing clients
- **2** Providing ongoing high quality customer service aimed at achieving targets
- 3 Implement customer service policies and procedures to ensure consistent customer service and satisfaction
- 4 Contacting customers on a regular basis to ensure the service is up to the required standard
- 5 Communicate with management to spread awareness of potential problems Troubleshoots and resolves non-routine customer complaints
- 6 Conducting weekly / monthly meetings to portray to management all complaints encountered.
- 7 Follow up customer complaint resolutions and ensure Customer satisfaction.

Coldwell Banker from (01/08/2005 until 01/12/2005)

It's a multinational real state company

Direct Sales Rep:

- 1 Achieving the customer needs
- 2 Do the customer calls/visits
- 3 Submit daily activity report to sales manager
- 4 Submit monthly forecast to sales manager. Do Customer case studies/Offers.
- 5 Dealing with potential new customers
- 6 Winning major new business through usual sales techniques
- 7 Prepare action plans and schedules to identify specific targets and to project the number of contacts to be made Follow up on new leads and referrals resulting from field activity
- 8 Prepare a variety of status reports, including activity, closings, follow-up, and adherence to goals

Rotary Club as part time job during the college (01/07/2004 until 10/10/2004)

VIP International Co as part time job during the college (01/02/2004 until 01/04/2004)

Marketing & Sales Rep in both jobs

- 1 Responsible for opening new accounts with potential customers
- 2 Follow up inquiries and proposals
- 3 taking appointments with potential customers
- 4 Build and develop relationships with retailers providing business advice and resolution to
- 5 follow-up on customer complaints and any other customer requirements

Education

- 1 Bachelor of Commerce and Business Administration in English Section
- 2 Major in Foreign Trade

Skills & Studies

- 1 Experience in different systems like SAP & Oracle.
- 2 Preparing for CMA
- 3 Skilled user in most Microsoft Applications.
- 4 Fluent in English (Reading & Writing).
- 5 Fluent in Deutsch (Reading & Writing)
- 6 Good in French Language
- 7 Good searcher on the net.

courses_

- 1 Professional mailing & reporting course.
- 2 Communication skills courses.
- 3 Leadership courses.
- 4 Process improvement courses.
- 5 Safety committee course.